<?xml version="1.0"?>
<part
id="reference"
> <title
>Reference</title>

 <partintro
>  <para
>   The entries in this Reference are meant to provide in reasonable
   length an authoritative, complete, and formal summary about their
   respective subjects.  More information about the use of
   <productname
>PostgreSQL</productname>, in narrative, tutorial, or
   example form, can be found in other parts of this book.  See the
   cross-references listed on each reference page.
  </para>

  <para
>   The reference entries are also available as traditional
   <quote
>man</quote> pages.
  </para>
 </partintro>

 <reference
id="sql-commands"
>  <title
>SQL Commands</title>

  <partintro
>   <para
>    This part contains reference information for the
    <acronym
>SQL</acronym> commands supported by
    <productname
>PostgreSQL</productname>.  By <quote
>SQL</quote> the
    language in general is meant; information about the standards
    conformance and compatibility of each command can be found on the
    respective reference page.
   </para>
  </partintro>

   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   

 </reference>

 <reference
id="reference-client"
>  <title
>PostgreSQL Client Applications</title>

  <partintro
>   <para
>    This part contains reference information for
    <productname
>PostgreSQL</productname> client applications and
    utilities.  Not all of these commands are of general utility; some
    might require special privileges.  The common feature of these
    applications is that they can be run on any host, independent of
    where the database server resides.
   </para>

   <para
>    When specified on the command line, user and database names have
    their case preserved  the presence of spaces or special
    characters might require quoting.  Table names and other identifiers
    do not have their case preserved, except where documented, and
    might require quoting.
   </para>
  </partintro>

   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   

 </reference>

 <reference
id="reference-server"
>  <title
>PostgreSQL Server Applications</title>

  <partintro
>   <para
>    This part contains reference information for
    <productname
>PostgreSQL</productname> server applications and
    support utilities.  These commands can only be run usefully on the
    host where the database server resides.  Other utility programs
    are listed in <xref
linkend="reference-client"
>.
   </xref></para>
  </partintro>

   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
   
